All right, okay, so we're starting a new מסכת תמורה, Masechet Temurah,
like a lot of these other מסכתות masechtot at the end of
קדשים, Kodashim, it has about 30 דף, daf, so they're all about
a month each.
תמורה Temurah is a fascinating מסכת masechet particularly at the beginning
because the phenomenon is a fascinating one and we'll see that as
soon as we start the משנה, mishna, which is that there's a
prohibition to try to do a תמורה. temurah. לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר
אתו טוב ברע או רע בטוב, Lo yachalifenu velo yamir oto tov
bera o ra betov, again, one of the פסוקים psukim right there
at the end of בחוקתי, Bechukotai, the same way ערכין, Erchin, we're
dealing with that section in the תורה Torah as well. And the
thing is, although you have done a negative prohibition, ואם המר ימיר
בהמה בבהמה, Ve'im hamir yamir behema bebehema, if you went ahead and
did this, והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש, vehaya hu utmurato yihye kodesh,
there's an impact to your act, a halachic impact. Obviously, there can
be a halachic impact to acts you do that are sins and
violations. If you murder somebody, he's still dead. Okay, but here, you
would think that you tried to transfer, you violated, maybe the תורה
Torah should not acknowledge what you've tried to do. Now, of course,
you didn't actually achieve everything you tried to do because you tried
to remove it from animal A and place it on animal B,
and you're now left with animal A remains קדוש kadosh and animal
B also becomes קדוש. kadosh. But nevertheless, there was a halachic impact
to your action. And as a result of this, and this will
be discussed right at the beginning, but as a result of this,
it gets into a fascinating discussion. Anybody, people even who have never
learned קדשים Kodashim at all, learn a מחלוקת machloket we're going to
have here at the beginning whether the general rule is if you
try to do something that's a violation, does it have halachic impact
or not? Again, not the physical reality, that obviously, but can it
change something's halachic status if you violated what the תורה Torah said?
Here's an example where it does. So let's take a look with
this right at the beginning. הכל ממירין, Hakol memirin, everybody can do
תמורה. temurah. אחד אנשים ואחד נשים, Echad anashim ve'echad nashim, whether men
or women. And now the משנה mishna itself encapsulates this idea
here that it's a violation but it has an effect. לא שאדם
רשאי להמיר, Lo she'adam rashai lehamir, I didn't mean to say everybody's
allowed to do תמורה. temurah. You're not allowed.
אלא שאם המיר מומר, Ella she'im hemir mumar,
the sanctity transferred, not fully, it didn't leave the first one, but
the second animal became sanctified. So when we said ממירין, memirin, we
mean there's an impact to your act of תמורה. temurah. Okay, but
let's not forget, וסופג את הארבעים, vesofeg et ha'arba'im, you get 40
lashes for having done it. And that is again what is fascinating,
that so much of the מסכת masechet talks about the effect of
תמורה. temurah. Does it transfer in this case? Does it transfer in
that case? What's the status of the second animal? Can you bring
the second animal as a קרבן? korban? And you could forget that
every single scenario we're discussing about means that somebody transgressed a negative
prohibition and deserves 40 lashes. So it puts that right up front
in the משנה, mishna, but also in a way to let you
know for a lot of this מסכת masechet we're going to be
talking about the impact of your actions and we're going to be
ignoring the fact that you've actually done a sin. Okay, but if
cases of these are all cases when somebody has violated and gets
the lashes. Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. הא
גופא
קשיא, Ha gufa kashya, the language of the משנה mishna is difficult.
אמרת הכל ממירין, Amarta hakol memirin, everybody can do a תמורה. temurah.
It sounds like you're allowed לכתחילה, l'chatchila,
that you can do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. והדר תני, Vahadar tani, then
we said לא שאדם רשאי להמיר, lo she'adam rashai lehamir, oh, but
you're not allowed to do it. דיעבד, Di'avad, so we're only talking
about post-facto, what's the impact? So the גמרא Gemara says, what kind
of question is that? תסברה, Tishbera, does that make sense that you're
asking me this question? הכל ממירין לכתחילה, Hakol memirin l'chatchila, that you
could think הכל ממירין hakol memirin means לכתחילה? l'chatchila? If that's what
you think it means in the משנה, mishna, קשיא לך ממתניתין, kashya
lach mi'matnitin, you're bothered, oh, then the משנה mishna says you're not
allowed and it starts by saying you are allowed. תסברה לך קרא,
Tishbera lach k'ra, you should just say it's going against the פסוק.
pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says דכתיב, dichtiv, לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אתו,
lo yachalifenu velo yamir oto,
don't try to transfer the קדושה. kedusha. אלא אמר רב יהודה הכי
קתני, Ella amar Rav Yehuda hachi katani, so okay, so the question
is fine, we get it. We never thought that the word הכל
ממירין hakol memirin meant you're allowed. It's clear from the פסוק, pasuk,
it's clear from the end of the משנה, mishna, but what is
meant by using that terminology? Why didn't we start by saying you
know, why don't we use a term that means that if you
did it, it works? Why do we use that terminology? So the
גמרא Gemara said, אלא אמר רב יהודה הכי קתני, Ella amar Rav
Yehuda hachi katani, this is really what the word תמורה temurah means
here. הכל מתפיסין בתמורה, Hakol matpisin b'temurah,
everybody can cause קדושה kedusha to transfer through their תמורה. temurah. So
when you say you do תמורה, temurah, right, it doesn't mean the
act of saying it and then of course you're not allowed to
do the act, you're in violation. But if you say you can
do תמורה, temurah, what we mean is your act of תמורה temurah
can be effective. So הכל ממירין hakol memirin doesn't mean you're allowed
to do the act, it means everybody can do the act in
a way that it will be effective. הכל מתפיסין בתמורה, Hakol matpisin
b'temurah, אחד אנשים ואחד נשים, echad anashim ve'echad nashim, whether men or
women. לא שאדם רשאי להמיר, Lo she'adam rashai lehamir, just to be
clear, you're not allowed to do the act. אלא שאם המיר מומר,
Ella she'im hemir mumar, but what we mean is it will be
effective. וסופג את הארבעים, Vesofeg et ha'arba'im, you get 40 lashes.
So yes, I understand the question because the whole enterprise of the
גמרא Gemara is based on parsing these linguistic quirks or rules of
the משנה. mishna. Right, so by using... using that term הכל hakol,
*hakol*, that I guess the question really is why are you using
the term הכל *hakol*? I mean, it's obvious within the context of
the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* what it means, right? Because it explains it.
Oh, you mean אנשים ונשים *anashim venashim*? But it didn't say that.
Then it would have said הכל לאתויי מאי *hakol le'atuyei mai*, which
is what it's actually about to say. And you can't say just
men and women because that's the end of the משנה mishnah *Mishnah*.
That's a different question, הכל *hakol*. Here it's the ממירים *mamirim* אף
*af* לכתחילה *lechatchilah* language. So the question here it's asking is, okay,
I get that it doesn't mean you're allowed. That's what the end
of the משנה mishnah, *Mishnah* says. That's what the פסוקים *pesukim* make
clear. But then what does the word mean? Then it says הכל
ממירים *hakol mamirim*, just the translation, translate that word for me. So
you can't translate the word as everybody is allowed to do תמורה
tmura, *temurah*. So the way you translate the word is everybody can
be effective in their תמורה tmura *temurah*. Everybody, everybody's act of תמורה
tmura, *temurah* will be effective. That's how you translate the word ממירים
*mamirim*. Yes.
So you're saying this discussion basically, we realize that people have flaws
and try to sort of analyze their flaws from...
Well, we realize that people sin, yes, and and
this is not a psychological analysis of the sin of their sin,
this is actually a discussion of the תורה Torah, *Torah*'s imposing of
this הלכה halacha. *halachah*. Now one interesting question to ask, which we
will get to in a few minutes, is how you understand והיה
הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש *ve-hayah hu utemurato yihyeh kodesh*. Do you understand
that as a natural result of his act, or do you understand
that as the תורה Torah *Torah* punishing him for his act? Right?
You can understand the difference, meaning, okay, you did a sin, but
even whether you had or hadn't did a sin, that would have
been the effect of doing תמורה tmura. *temurah*. Somehow the קדושה kedusha
*kedushah* is so sticky that it can't remove from the original one,
but your act of attempting it does does put קדושה kedusha, *kedushah*
on the second animal. Meaning that's a natural effect of doing תמורה
temurah. *temurah* regardless of whether you've sinned or not. Or no, had
it been that you hadn't sinned, maybe the act would have been
meaningless. But the תורה Torah *Torah*, or who knows what, but the
תורה Torah *Torah* wants to punish you. You tried to do this
thing, ha, you're going to get you're going to have to not
only is, you know, you know, you're going to have to suffer
doubly, let's suffer whatever, but you're going to lose out. The second
animal becomes קדוש kadosh, *kadosh* and the first one. So that's the
question, right, about the relationship of the prohibited nature of the act
and the effect of the act. Is that clear, my question? Is
the effect of תמורה temurah, *temurah* a natural result the same way
I can sanctify, if I did תמורה temurah *temurah* the natural metaphysical
laws of קדושה kedusha, *kedushah* mean that the קדושה kedusha *kedushah* will
apply to the second animal and stay with the first? Or no,
it's only what the תורה *Torah* is imposing essentially as a fine
for my having violated. Okay, we'll see that question in a minute.
Okay, but the first point is that the word ממירים *mamirim* in
the משנה *Mishnah* means that their act is effective. Let's take a
look. Now we're going to get to the question Dov raised, which
is what is הכל *hakol*? הכל לאתויי מאי *hakol le'atuyei mai*? What
do you mean everybody? It can't just mean men and women, that's
what the משנה *Mishnah* says, so it must mean something else. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לאתויי יורש yoresh *le'atuyei yoresh*. It's coming
to include an heir. That if somebody inherits his father's קרבן korban
*korban*, so you know, only the owner of the קרבן korban, *korban*
can do תמורה temurah, *temurah*, right? Only the owner of the קרבן
korban, *korban* was in a position to try to remove the קדושה
kedusha *kedushah* and place it on another. Well, how do you define
owner of the קרבן korban. *korban*? Let's say the guy died and
now his son inherited the animal and his son would bring the
קרבן korban. *korban* for his father, but he didn't start it, he
didn't sanctify it. Is he in a position to try to remove
it and to place it on the other animal? Will that be
effective in the laws of תמורה temurah. *temurah*? Now again, you could
also ask the question about will he get lashes? Right? If I
walk up to Dov's קרבן korban *korban* and I say I'm transferring
the קדושה kedusha, *kedushah* from A to B, it was a meaningless
act, so I don't even get lashes. So you know, you could
always ask the question about the violation or the effect. But here
it's asking the question about the effect.
Does it apply to let's say כהנים kohanim *kohanim* or those who
are in charge of it once it's been handed over to the...
Yeah, but they're never seen in a position to to effect the
קדושה kedusha, *kedushah*, so there would be like never a הוה אמינא
hava amina, *havah amina* about the כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*. It's always just
about the owner, but how do you define the owner? We'll see
a couple of possibilities of that today. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says ודלא כרבי יהודה *udelo k'Rabbi Yehuda*, not like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda's *Rabbi Yehuda* who says the heir is not in a
position to do this. דתנן d'tenan, *Detnan* or דתניא detanya, *detanya* rather,
we learn a ברייתא braita, *baraita*, יורש סומך somech יורש ממיר דברי
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *yoresh somech, yoresh mamir, divrei Rabbi Meir*. So
obviously these are linked ideas. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* thinks
that the heir, somebody who inherits his father's קרבן korban *korban*, is
considered to be the the owner of the קרבן korban. *korban*. He
will bring it for his father and he is like the owner.
So therefore, number one, when he brings it, he does סמיכה smicha,
*semichah*. Who does סמיכה smicha? *semichah* on the קרבן korban, *korban*? Only
the owner does סמיכה smicha? *semichah*, not somebody else. If I ask
you to bring my קרבן korban *korban* for me, I can't get
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*, could you please bring
this to the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*? You can do that for
me, I don't have to be present, but you're not going to
do סמיכה smicha. *semichah*. So he says the heir becomes like the
new owner, he does סמיכה smicha. *semichah*, and because he's like the
new owner, he also is in a position to do תמורה temurah,
*temurah*, okay, which again, remember, is not a good thing, but okay,
he's in a position to do תמורה temurah, *temurah*. That's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר יורש
אינו סומך ויורש אינו ממיר *Rabbi Yehuda omer yoresh eino somech veyoresh
eino mamir*. No, he's not the new owner. He'll bring it, but
now the owner is the dead father, and therefore he's not the
owner, he doesn't do סמיכה smicha *semichah* and he can't do תמורה
temurah, *temurah*. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama, דרבי יהודה *Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda*?
What's the reason of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* that excludes
the heir? יליף תחלת הקדש מסוף הקדש *Yalif techilat hekdesh misof hekdesh*.
He learns the beginning from the end. מה סוף הקדש יורש אינו
סומך *Mah sof hekdesh yoresh eino somech*, the same way at the
end of the process a יורש *yoresh* cannot do סמיכה smicha. *semichah*,
which we'll prove in a minute, אף תחלת הקדש יורש אינו ממיר
*af techilat hekdesh yoresh eino mamir*. Even at the beginning he doesn't
do תמורה temurah. *temurah*. Now תמורה temurah *temurah* is sometimes called the
beginning, sometimes called the end. It's the beginning of הקדש *hekdesh* in
the sense of... Because as far as this animal is concerned, the
act that started it off as a קרבן korban was the act
of תמורה, temurah right? So that from that perspective it's the beginning
of a process. Sometimes תמורה temurah is called the end of a
process because it only came after the first animal was sanctified. But
anyway here we're calling it the beginning. So it says like this.
It says as I said to you, these are linked concepts, right?
The question is basically do we view the heir as the owner
of the קרבן korban or not? So it says since Rabbi Yehuda
comes from the position that he's not the owner vis-a-vis
סמיכה, smicha. סוף תכתי, sof tachtei, it's also going to say that
he's not the owner vis-a-vis תמורה, temurah תחילה תכתי. techila tachtei. All
right? So he does not view him as the owner. Now how
do we know it by סמיכה? smicha וסמיכה גופא מנלן, U'smicha gufa
minalan, where do we know that according to Rabbi Yehuda at least,
an heir cannot do סמיכה? smicha, תלתא קרבנו כתיבי. Tlata korbano ktivi.
It says by שלמים, shlamim, he shall bring his קרבן, korban his
קרבן, korban. his קרבן. korban. It says קרבנו korbano three times. So
each one is to come and there it is coming, it's understood
to be right there in the context of סמיכה. smicha So it
is understood that there's a high sense of ownership that is needed
for סמיכה. smicha And here's what we're going to learn now by
the three times. חד קרבנו ולא קרבן עובד כוכבים, Chad korbano velo
korban oved kochavim, one to say his and not that of a
non-Jew. So his not meaning personal ownership alone, but here actually meaning
just his in the sense of Jewish קרבן. korban. Now that's important.
We're going to continue to talk about today and we've talked about
before that a non-Jew can sanctify קרבנות, korbanot, can bring קרבנות korbanot
and so on. However, the non-Jew is excluded from סמיכה smicha in
two ways. Number one is that when he brings his קרבן korban.
he doesn't do סמיכה. smicha There the גמרא Gemara learns it from
a פסוק pasuk that says דבר אל בני ישראל, Daber el Bnei
Yisrael, בני ישראל סומכין, Bnei Yisrael somchin, the more famous דרשה drasha
is בני ישראל סומכין ואין בנות ישראל סומכות. Bnei Yisrael somchin ve'ein
bnot Yisrael somchot. We're not doing that today. But it is בני
ישראל סומכין ולא עובדי כוכבים סומכין. Bnei Yisrael somchin velo ovdei kochavim
somchin. They bring their קרבן korban, they can't do סמיכה. smicha. Fine.
But here's another question. The non-Jew has sent his קרבן. korban Maybe
the כהנים kohanim should do סמיכה smicha for him? Here's the כהנים.
kohanim Okay, so he doesn't do סמיכה, smicha, but maybe they're bringing
the קרבן, korban the owner, they maybe should represent him and maybe
they should do סמיכה smicha, for him. So it says no, his
קרבן korban, does not get סמיכה smicha. even if he's not doing
it, forget him, כהנים won't do it for his קרבן korban, either.
That's one exclusion. ולא קרבן עובד כוכבים. Velo korban oved kochavim. וחד
קרבנו ולא קרבן חברו, Vechad korbano velo korban chavero, his and not
your friend's. I have James bring a קרבן korban for me like
I mentioned before. He's able to bring that קרבן korban for me,
but since he's not the owner, he does not do סמיכה smicha
for me. You have to do סמיכה semicha, for your own thing.
By the way, the importance here, not about the non-Jew actually, but
the idea that it has to be you personally is very important
in terms of the whole concept of סמיכה. semicha, The whole concept
of סמיכה semicha, is basically to say, you know, emphasize your connection
to this animal and your sense of this is yours, it's not
just סתם stam a ritual. Maybe it's even to sort of say
the way some people think about certain types of קרבנות, korbanot, this
is my substitute, this is taking my place. That's a רמב"ן's Ramban
approach to קרבנות, korbanot, but even if you don't say that, it
emphasizes the personal connection to the קרבן. korban? So therefore, if you're
bringing it for me, fine, it could be brought without the personal
connection, but you can't play that role. It's no, it's not, you
should not be doing the סמיכה, semicha. it's not your קרבן. korban
Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara that's so that's קרבנו ולא קרבן חברו.
korbano velo korban chavero. And what's the third one? So the third
one is
where were we? ולא קרבן חברו וחד קרבנו ולא קרבן אביו, Velo
korban chavero vechad korbano velo korban aviv, only yours not your father's.
And therefore we exclude the heir. He is not enough of an
owner of the owner of this קרבן. korban That's what Rabbi Yehuda
said. So once you don't do סמיכה, semicha. you don't do תמורה.
temurah. You're not in the, you're not, it's not considered yours. ולרבי
מאיר דאמר יורש סומך, U'lerabi Meir de'amar yoresh somech, and according to
Rabbi Meir that says he can do it, what does he do
with the fact that it says קרבנו? korbano? No, ההוא, hahu, that
third one, מיבעי ליה לרבות כל בעלי חוברין לסמיכה. mibaei lei lerabot
kol ba'alei chovrin l'smicha. That there actually it's inclusive, not exclusive, that
let's say you have a partnership קרבן. korban, Three of us get
together and decide we're going to bring an עולה olah or a
שלמים. shlamim. Believe it or not you're allowed to do that. So
each one of us has to do סמיכה. semicha. קרבנו Korbano here
means of each owner, not just to exclude somebody who's a quasi-owner,
but to indicate each owner has to do it if there are
multiple owners. That's what he learned.
Rabbi Yehuda as a group?
No, presumably
that's a good question. You mean do they all do it at
the same time? I don't know if they can all get their
hands on the head of an animal at the same time. My
assumption here was individually. But that's an interesting question. If it was
physically possible, would it be preferred to do it as a group?
Possibly. It's an interesting question. Rabbi Yehuda, what would Rabbi Yehuda say
back? בעלי חוברין לסמיכה לית ליה. Ba'alei chovrin l'smicha leit lei. No,
he actually would reject that הלכה. halacha He would say that you
don't do it if it's a group. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why?
דלא מיוחד קרבן דידיה, Delo meyuchad korban didei, because it doesn't have,
and that actually makes sense conceptually. The same Rabbi Yehuda that is
really emphasizing the personal connection and excludes the case of the heir,
he's also going to exclude the case of a partnership. When it's
a partnership, you don't have that intense personal connection. It's more of
a corporate sort of, you know, relationship. And therefore because you don't
have that intense personal connection, you won't be סומך in that
case. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, maybe he does hold that each member
does סמיכה semicha in that case. So where does he learn it
from? וקרבן עובד כוכבים וקרבן חברו מחד קרא נפקא. V'korban oved kochavim
v'korban chavero mechad kra nafka. That really you don't need a separate
פסוק pasuk for the non-Jew case and for the case of the
of the what do you call of somebody doing it for me.
Because since we already said the non-Jew doesn't do it himself, and
since the only scenario that we're asking about the non-Jew is when
he sends his קרבן, korban can the כהנים do it for him?
So conceptually that's the same thing as can my friend do it
for me? And therefore you only need one פסוק pasuk to exclude
both of those scenarios, the non-Jew and the friend, because in both
cases it means can somebody who's not the owner do it? No.
So that he gets from one פסוק, pasuk, the other פסוק pasuk
is the heir, and the third פסוק pasuk is all members of
a group. The קרבן חטאת korban chatat of והקריבו אחד, ve'hikrivo echad,
there he has one extra קרבן korban. although בעלי חובות ba'alei chovot
all members of the group. Fine. So that is רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda position. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, says that an heir cannot do
סמיכה, semicha. קרבנו korbano no, and because he's not considered the owner
of the קרבן korban? vis-a-vis סמיכה, semicha, he's also not the owner
of it vis-a-vis תמורה. temurah? Now we're going to look at רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir דאמר יורש ממימר de'amar yoresh
meimir that says an heir can do סמיכה, smicha מאי טעמא, what's
the reason? תוספות Tosafot by the way points out the obvious problem.
How come you're asking both for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. and רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda? which is the reason? Shouldn't it be a default
position? So anyway, he raises that. But the point is anyway the
גמרא Gemara is exploring what motivates each position. So רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is motivated by יורש and that's what he read into קרבנו
korbano by סמיכה. smicha. I mean he's motivated by קרבנו korbano by
סמיכה. smicha What motivates רבי מאיר to be inclusive of the heir?
Again, remember inclusivity is not necessarily a good thing by תמורה, temurah,
okay? It means that you can get lashes, it means your other
animal is also קדוש, kadosh. but okay. Anyway, what makes him include
the heir? אמר לך, amar lach, it says המיר ימיר. hamir yamir.
If if if a double language, if תמורה temurah, is done, both
it and the other will be קדוש. But that double language is
like inclusive, seems to be no matter what. So what does that
mean? לרבות היורש, lerabbot hayoresh, even if the heir does it. And
now once you have an heir doing doing תמורה, temurah you can
also have the heir doing סמיכה. smicha. There's linked ideas about him
being the owner of the קרבן, korban. ויליף סוף הקדש מתחילת הקדש,
ve'yalif sof hekdesh mi'techilat hekdesh, it learns the end of the process
סמיכה smicha from the beginning of the process the sanctifying it in
תמורה. temurah מה תחילת הקדש יורש ממימר, mah techilat hekdesh yoresh meimir,
the same way in the beginning of the process we've shown that
the heir can do תמורה, temurah אף סוף הקדש יורש סומך, af
sof hekdesh yoresh somech, even at the end of the process he
can do, meaning of a normal קרבן, korban, not his תמורה, temurah.
but anyway, he can do סמיכה. Okay, he is considered the owner
of the of the קרבן korban he inherits. רבי יהודה, האי המיר
ימיר מאי עביד ליה? hai hamir yamir mai avid lei? What does
he do with that double language since he does not include an
heir, רבי יהודה? לרבות
את
האשה,
lerabbot et
ha'ishah,
that's how we know it's to include women. וכן תניא, ve'chein tanya,
and we thought in a ברייתא, braita this goes back to our
משנה that says men and women. We're focusing on the heir. How
do you know both men and women? Now we're going to spell
that out. As the ברייתא braita says, לפי שכל הענין כולו אינו
מדבר אלא בלשון זכר, lefi she'kol ha'inyan kulo eino medaber ela bi'leshon
zachar, the whole parsha is written in the male, שנאמר she'ne'emar as
most of the תורה, לא יחליפנו, lo yachlifenu, you should not, you
the man, יחליפנו yachlifenu should not try to exchange it, as opposed
to לא תחליפנו, lo tachlifenu, ולא ימיר אותו, ve'lo yamir oto, and
you should not exchange it. So if it's all written in the
male, אשה מנין, ishah minayin, how do I know women are in
this
פרשה? parsha? תלמוד לומר המיר ימיר לרבות את האשה, talmud lomar hamir
yamir lerabbot et ha'ishah, if he will under any circumstances do תמורה,
temurah? meaning and whoever the המיר hamir doesn't have the יוד yud
anyway that makes it male. So therefore even a woman does תמורה.
temurah? Just as you said, the whole תורה is written in לשון
זכר.
leshon zachar. Right, which the גמרא Gemara is basically going to ask
in a minute, okay, soon. When would we have excluded women from
a negative prohibition and the whole תורה is written in לשון זכר?
leshon zachar? So we'll see that in a minute. But first we're
going to sort of deal with working out the דרשות. drashot.
What? Anyway, almost all. ולרבי מאיר אשה מנא ליה? u'le'Rabbi Meir ishah
mena lei? And how then does רבי מאיר include a woman if
the המיר hamir is coming to include an heir? נפקא ליה מואם,
nafka lei mi've'im, ואם המיר ימיר, ve'im hamir yamir, the extra ואו
vav is coming to be inclusive of another way, even include women.
רבי יהודה ואם לא דריש, Rabbi Yehuda ve'im lo darish, he's not
impressed with the ואו vav and therefore it's not he doesn't have
to deal with it. Okay, so now we've dealt with how one
approach learns out an heir, the other not. Interesting question which is
both about תמורה temurah and סמיכה, is somebody who inherited his father's
קרבן korban... considered to be the new owner of the קרבן? korban,
Okay, and our משנה that says הכל, the גמרא Gemara. understands it
means to include even the heir like רבי מאיר. Now we're going
to focus our attention on the issue of women, which is the
main point of the משנה, which we just and the and the
ברייתא braita we just quoted. Yes.
Because you asked if רבי יהודה says he doesn't include women.
No, no, everybody says includes women based on המיר ימיר, hamir yamir,
the extra ואו, vav, everybody says includes women.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ובין רבי מאיר ובין רבי יהודה דהאי דריבי קרא לאשה, u'vein Rabbi
Meir u'vein Rabbi Yehuda de'hai de'ribi kra le'ishah, now let's get back
to the ברייתא Baraita. that the פסוק pasuk included a woman, ואם
המיר ימיר ve'im hamir yamir somehow with an extra language to include
a woman. אי לאו דריבי קרא, ei lav de'ribi kra, if the
פסוק pasuk hadn't said something extra, הוה אמינא דעבד תמורה לא לקי,
hava amina de'avad temurah lo laki, I would have thought that if
she tried to do it she wouldn't get
lashes? What's special about המיר? hamir? It's a negative prohibition. How would
I have thought to exclude her? דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, de'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name
of רב, Rav, וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, ve'chein tana de'vei Rabbi
Yishmael, and even taught in the
house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
at a tannaic level, איש או אשה כי יעשו מכל חטאת האדם,
ish o ishah ki ya'asu mi'kol chatot ha'adam, if they do any
of the sins of people, השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל עונשים שבתורה,
hishvah ha'katuv ishah le'ish le'chol onashim she'ba'Torah, man and women are to
be treated the same. It's צריכא, tzricha, I need it. מהו דתימא,
mahu d'teima, I might have thought, הני מילי, hani mili, only things,
עונש דשוה בין ביחיד בין בציבור, onesh d'shaveh bein b'yachid bein b'tzibur,
maybe that's things that apply not only that when things are equal,
they're also equal in other ways. Prohibitions that apply whether at the
individual level or the communal level. I'm funny, like how many sins
are communal sins? But anyway, but nevertheless, אבל הכא, aval hacha, כיון
דעונש שאינו שוה בכל הוא, keivan d'onesh she'eino shaveh b'chol hu,
this issue of תמורה temurah does not apply at the communal level.
How do I know? דתנן, אין הציבור והשותפין עושין תמורה. ein hatzibur
v'hashutfin osin temurah. If you have a communal קרבן korban. like a
קרבן תמיד korban tamid or a partnership קרבן korban like we were
discussing before, that תמורה temurah cannot be done. תמורה temurah. can only
be done when it's an individual, a private קרבן, korban, completely private.
So therefore, since in some ways certain people are excluded, right, so
groups and so on, so maybe also women would be excluded. It's
not one of these fully inclusive prohibitions. So מהו, mahu, I again,
it's a funny הוה אמינא, hava amina but nevertheless it would have
been a basis for distinguishing, one minute, אשה נמי כי עבדה לא
לקיא, isha nami ki avda lo lakya, maybe a woman would have
been excluded, wouldn't have gotten lashes, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that she does. Now רש״י Rashi has a different גירסא, girsa, completely
different גירסא girsa of the גמרא. Gemara He acknowledges this גירסא, girsa,
but he also has a different גירסא girsa that says this also
there's something special about תמורה. tmurah, What's special about תמורה? tmurah. Besides
the that that you did a prohibition and it had the impact,
that you do a prohibition without doing an action, just with speech.
And normally, if you just do a prohibition with speech, you don't
get lashes. You still transgress, but you don't get lashes. So we
say since this whole category is a חידוש, chiddush, that even a
speech act is considered an act and you get lashes, maybe although
we generally equate men and women for punishments and prohibitions, maybe this
case is such an such an exception that maybe for some reason
it's also an exception in terms of who's being referred to. And
now still that's pretty funny because, you know, the general rule always
is without something explicit to exclude women, the whole תורה is בלשון
זכר bilshon zachar and we assume women are included, but nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara is at least explaining what a possible הוה אמינא would
have been. Yes.
This distinguishes it from סמיכה that women
are are excluded.
So קרבן ציבור korban tzibur doesn't do תמורה, tmurah can't do תמורה,
tmurah but they do סמיכה.
Not ציבור, tzibur, but a קרבן korban but but but a קרבן
שותפין, korban shutfin, yes. Yes. קרבן שותפין korban shutfin is different. ציבור
tzibur is the entire כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. שותפין shutfin is a
small little group of people.
So it's not considered.
Right, right. What you do סמיכה on and what you do תמורה
tmurah, on. Oh, you mean because before we were comparing. Yes, that's
a good point. That was in terms of, yes, good point. I
mean, that was in terms of whether you're at all considered the
owner. The exclusion from תמורה tmurah. of a שותפות shutfut is not
that you're not the owner. Well, it's a good point. We'll get
back to it. It's not exactly that you're not the owner, but
it's that it's not the same type of ownership. So but you're
right that the גמרא Gemara before emphasized they were the same and
here we actually see a point of difference. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara asks starts asking an interesting question. Now that we mentioned women,
okay fine, women we understand, women are generally treated like men by
all of these ownership and so on. Let's talk about other people
that are not always treated the same way. And what is fascinating
about this discussion in my mind is it gets to the heart
of to what degree is the effect of תמורה tmurah connected to
the prohibition of תמורה. tmurah And if you had somebody that would
not be trans
would not be prohibited, would it still have the effect of transferring
the קדושה kedusha, to the other animal?
Obviously keeping it in the original animal. Basic exactly. Is it is
it a punishment? That's one way of framing it. Maybe it's not
the only way, but I think that's a simple way of framing
it. Is it a punishment for having transgressed and or is it
just a natural metaphysics of your act? So let's take a look.
בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar Chama. That's got to be
a great phrase, natural metaphysics. בעי רמי בר חמא, Ba'ei Rami bar
Chama, so רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asks the following question:
קטן מהו שימיר, katan mahu sheyamir, can a minor do תמורה? tmurah
Okay, so now it has to first of all be his קרבן.
korban How did he get his קרבן? So we're going to say
in a minute, remember a minor who is one year before בר
ובת מצוה bar v'bat mitzvah can do acts of הפלאה hafla'ah and
acts of speech acts whatever and can be מקדיש makdish and נדרים
nedarim and so on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא בקטן שלא הגיע לעונת נדרים,
ilima b'katan shelo higia l'onat nedarim, if he's not yet at this
age of making vows and speech acts, meaning he or she is
not a year before בר או בת מצוה, bar o bat mitzvah,
לא תיבעי לך, lo tibei lach, there's no question. דכיון דקדושה לא
אקדיש, d'keivan d'kedusha lo akdish, so since he can't make the קדושה,
kedusha, even a basic קדושה, kedusha אימורי מימר, imuri meimar, how could
he do תמורה? tmurah. Now by the way, that in itself is
not a crazy question. Maybe I don't have the power to create
יש מאין, yesh me'ayin, right, I don't have the power to create
קדושה kedusha, out of nothing, but if this animal already has קדושה
kedusha and I'm building on the existing קדושה, kedusha maybe I could
do תמורה tmurah, and transfer to the other thing. But I think
that so the קל וחומר kal v'chomer doesn't make so much sense,
but I think the point is what I said. You can't do
תמורה tmurah unless it's your קרבן. So of course if you can't
make your קרבן, how did you get a קרבן to make תמורה
tmurah. from? Okay, but it's an interesting קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, if
you can't make קדושה, kedusha, certainly you can't make תמורה. Temurah But
presumably it means what I said, if it's not your קרבן... what
are we talking about? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא כי קמיבעיא
ליה, ella ki kamibaya lei, what are we talking about? The קטן
שהגיע לעונת נדרים. katan shehigia le-onot nedarim. He's at the age where
he can make vows and he can make a קדושה, kedusha. a
year before בר בת מצוה. Bar Bat Mitzvah. מי אמרינן כיון דאמר
מר איש, Mi amrina kivan de-amar mar ish, since we say by
vows that the verse starts by saying if a man makes a
vow. But then we say מה תלמוד לומר כי יפלי נדר, mah
talmud lomar ki yafli neder, when he enunciates a vow, why doesn't
it just say כי ידור, ki yindor, you know, when he makes
a vow, כי ידור נדר, ki yindor neder, excuse me, why does
it use the word יפלי? yafli? לרבות מופלא הסמוך לאיש, Lerabot mufla
hasamuch le-ish, it's coming to include even somebody who is right before
בר בת מצוה Bar Bat Mitzvah that is able to make vows.
דקדושו קדוש, Dekadosho kadosh, that he's able to sanctify things and make
vows. So that's our principle, a year before בר בת מצוה, Bar
Bat Mitzvah, oh, I need I'm sorry, I needed to have added
and you understand who the, you know, that who the vow is
relating to God, the significance of the vow and so on. So
if it's clear that you understand what you're doing, and you're a
year before בר בת מצוה, Bar Bat Mitzvah, then you can make
vows and make sanctity. So, and maybe I would say, מדיאקדושי מקדיש,
mide-akdushei makdish, since he could make קדושה, kedusha, and if animal now
maybe is this animal that he sanctified, אמורי נמי ממר, amurei nami
mameir, he can do תמורה, Temurah meaning if it's all about the
metaphysics if you would, about the קדושה kedusha power, fine, you made
קדושה, kedusha you sanctified it, you can also transfer קדושה kedusha and
do תמורה. Temurah. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, כיון
דלאו בר עונשין הוא, kivan delav bar onshin hu, since he's not
prohibited yet, he's not yet an adult and he's not prohibited by
the, by the Torah's prohibition, תמורה נמי לא מיתפסא, tmurah nami lo
mitfsa, so then the תמורה Temurah, won't be effective. So I think
that is such a great question, right? He has the power to
do these קדושה kedusha, things, but he's not prohibited. Is the תמורה
Temurah. an effect of his power to, you know, do קדושה, kedusha.
or is it an effect of him having transgressed and therefore, that's
the question about whether it will be effective or not. He would
do סמיכה. What? He would do סמיכה presumably, right? Unless there's another
פסוק pasuk to exclude that. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: או דילמא כיון דלאו בר עונשין הוא תמורה לא מיתפסא. O
dilma, kivan delav bar onshin hu, tmurah lo mitfsa. And it doesn't
answer. And then it goes on. אם תמצא לומר קטן עביד תמורה,
Im timtza lomar katan avid tmurah, now, let's say you say he
could do תמורה, Temurah which is an amazing אם תמצא לומר, im
timtza lomar, it just accepts it, okay, maybe yes. But maybe דאתי
לכלל עונשין. de-ati likhlal onshin. Maybe that's because eventually he will become
an adult. He will and he will be punishable. Okay, however, עובד
כוכבים oved kochavim מהו שימיר? mahu she-yamir? What about a non-Jew? Now,
a non-Jew has the power to sanctify, but he's not certainly never
will be prohibited by the laws of a תמורה. Temurah מי אמר
מדיאקדושי מקדיש, Mi amar mide-akdushei makdish, since he can
sanctify, דתניא ותני בריתא, detanya ve-tani beraisa, איש איש, ish ish, if
any man brings a קרבן, מה תלמוד לומר איש איש, mah talmud
lomar ish ish, what's this double language any
man? לרבות את העובדי כוכבים Lerabot et ha-ovedei kochavim שנודרין נדרים ונדבות
כישראל, she-nodrin nedarim u-nedavot ke-yisrael, they can make sanctify animals like Jews.
So since I he has the power to sanctify, אמורי נמי ממר,
amurei nami mameir, he can also do a תמורה Temurah. on his
קרבן. או דילמא, O dilma, or do I say, כיון דלאו אתי
לכלל עונשין, kivan delav ati likhlal onshin, since he's not in the
category of punishment, כי עביד תמורה לא קדשה, ki avid tmurah lo
kadsha, so the תמורה tmura. will also not be sanctified. So again
we are asking this question. Now the question is why do we
think a קטן katan the significance that he's דאתי לכלל עונשין? ati
likhlal onshin? You can frame it in one of two ways. One
way, which I think is what the גמרא Gemara is getting at,
is keeping within this model of תמורה tmura. as a consequence of
sin. The wages of sin, right? So and so the point is
okay, you know what, a קטן katan right now hasn't sinned. But
the idea of this being a sin is relevant to him. And
therefore, once the Torah has this as the consequences of sin, it
has it even for the קטן katan even though personally it's not
a sin for him, it will soon be a sin for him
and therefore it's a relevant concept. Whereas for a non-Jew, you can't
even frame this as a consequence of sin, it's completely, you know,
irrelevant, the idea of sin to this act of תמורה. tmura. That's
one way and still keeping you within the concept of a, if
you would, a fine or a consequence of of a sinful act.
If you want to do it like that way, it's a consequence
of a sinful act even if I personally didn't sin. So for
the minor he didn't sin, but it was a sinful act, whereas
for the non-Jew completely not. That's I think the גמרא Gemara trying
to keep its framework of is this about sin, or is this
about the metaphysics and about the קדושה. kedusha Another way of saying
it though which is not so much that way is that by
the con- that it's less of a concept now of sin all
of- and it's more of a concept of are you in the
פרשה parsha or not. Okay, meaning, you know, for a lot of
things Jews can do, you know, a minor for example can do
שחיטה, shechita, a non-Jew can't do שחיטה, shechita, right? It has nothing
to do with the fact about whether there's a מצוה mitzvah on
the Jew or the non-Jew. It has to do with the fact
that, you know, for you're in the פרשה parsha of שחיטה, shechita,
you're within the Jew category of all these הלכות, halachot, so your
acts can be meaningful. Somebody who's outside can't be. So, you know,
that's a way of thinking of the גמרא Gemara, question. That the
קטן katan is in the category of תמורה, tmura? not sin, I
guess again. He's in the פרשה parsha of תמורה because he'll eventually
be an adult, so therefore he has the metaphysics of תמורה. A
non-Jew who's never in the פרשה parsha to begin with
is outside. Meaning it's a similar thing, but it's no longer about
consequence of sin, it's about whether you relate to the category. In
my mind, the question is still very much focused on the question
of sin. And it's a question about do we view תמורה as
a consequence of a sin or sinful act, or do we view
it as a metaphysics and therefore a great test case is the
non-Jew. Because the non-Jew has the power of קדושה, kedusha, but it's
irrelevant to him the idea of this as a sin or sinful
act. And will there be תמורה for the non-Jew? Do you want
to add something, Dov?
No, the קטן katan will inevitably become...
Right, which is why the גמרא's Gemara, willing to concede the קטן.
katan. Yes, but I mean a non-Jew
can be מתגייר. mitgayer. Yeah, but then he's not, but that's not
in his... Yes, but it's like the whole קטן שנולד katan shenolad
and it's not שייך shayach to the world of non-Jews as... it's
not natural, yeah, that's never sort of been the... I should say
that רש"י Rashi by the way is somehow jumps in right away
and says, oh, even though we're doing the אם תמצי לומר, im
timtzi lomar, this is all just hypothetical. Of course the הלכה halachic
is that a קטן katan can't do תמורה. So it's interesting why
רש"י Rashi felt that that was so obvious and jumped in and
said that. The גמרא, Gemara I don't think it is so obvious.
It's really considering that possibility. Okay, but if that's true, that a
קטן katan can't do תמורה, and this is all just hypothetical, well
at least then according to רש"י, Rashi, the bottom line is that
it is about sin. And even though the קטן katan has the
full קדושה kedusha. powers, the קטן katan that's near בר ובת מצוה,
bar u'bat mitzvah, nevertheless, because it's not yet a sin for this
קטן, katan, it would not do תמורה. And that's at least what
רש"י Rashi says in conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara but we're going
to still deal with the hypothetical.
If תמורה doesn't work, does that mean the קדושה kedusha doesn't move?
No, nothing happens. Right, that's the assumption. That if it doesn't work,
then nothing happens.
Other examples of cases where where קטן katan something a קטן katan
is effective at doing something that a non-Jew is not effective?
Oh, are there other cases? Sure, I mean, you know, there's questions
about let's say כתיבת גט ketivat get that requires לשמה, lishma, that
if a non-Jew does it over with Jewish supervision and adult supervision
it works, if a non-Jew does it it doesn't work. And a
קטן katan does work.
A קטן katan does work.
You're asking cases where a קטן katan does work and a non-Jew
doesn't. Yeah, yeah. There are a lot of הלכה acts that require
a Jew and could be done with a קטן katan but not,
you know, but not with a non-Jew or a קטן katan with
adult supervision. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So now we're going
to try to start answering that question. So let's take a look.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so we framed the question, let's start trying
to answer it. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דתניא, we
taught in the ברייתא. קדשי עובדי כוכבים Kodshei ovdei kochavim לא נהנין
ולא מועלין. lo nehenin v'lo moalin. The sacrifices of non-Jews, although we
said they can make sacrifices and sanctify animals, they don't have the
same קדושה kedusha level as the sanctified things of Jews. First of
all, you're not allowed to derive benefit, obviously at least rabbinically, but
nevertheless לא מועלין, lo moalin, you do not transgress the biblical prohibition
of מעילה. meilah. They are sanctified but not at the highest level.
ואין חייבין עליהם, V'ein chayavin aleihem, and similarly, you do not transgress
when you bring this sacrifice, so a כהן kohen is to bring
the sacrifice of a non-Jew, משום פיגול נותר וטמא. mishum pigul notar
v'tamei. All these, all these prohibitions that you can have with sacrifices,
if you have the wrong thoughts and to eat it at the
wrong time or you leave it over, if it becomes טמא, tamei,
all these, all these things are so severe
prohibitions because they are violating the קדושה, kedusha right? They're somehow affronting
the קדושה. kedusha So because the... I'm trying to give you the
reason here, these are not arbitrary points. The assumption here is that
the sacrifice of non-Jews don't have the same level of קדושה kedusha,
and therefore even when there's they're problematic, they're טמא, tamei, נותר, notar,
whatever, it is not... you don't have the sin. Okay, because it
is not the same sort of sense of affront to the קדושה,
kedusha. violation to the קדושה. kedusha, אין עושין תמורה, Ein osin Temurah,
not only that, if you cannot do תמורה with the קרבן of
a non-Jew. So there you go, just answered our question. Okay, you
can't do תמורה. Now again, you could frame this again at the
קדושה kedusha. level. If the קדושה's kedusha. weaker, it can't extend beyond
its original location, right? It's only if a powerful קדושה kedusha can
it possibly extend beyond. So אין עושין תמורה, ein osin Temurah, ואין
מביאין נסכים, v'ein mevi'in nesachim, and non-Jews do not bring נסכים, nesachim,
which again, רש"י Rashi takes out the word עליהם aleihem because there's
a whole question, it seems like actually you do bring נסכים, nesachim,
which is the wine and the flour and the oil on the
sacrifice of non-Jews, and they can even sometimes pay for it, but
they are brought with the sacrifice. So רש"י Rashi actually says it
means no, no, no, they just can't bring נסכים nesachim separately. He
takes out the word עליהם. aleihem. But that's bizarre because then it
really has very little to do with the sacrifice itself, but maybe
something that normally you can connect your your נסכים nesachim to your
sacrifice even many days later, but here for a non-Jew it would
have to only be brought literally together with it. Okay, that's אין
מביאין נסכים עליהם. ein mevi'in nesachim aleihem. אבל קרבנותיו
נסכים, Aval korbanotav nesachim, as it says right here, you do bring
נסכים nesachim for the animal, so what does that mean? Does it
mean he doesn't bring it or does it mean that no, no,
no, you can't bring it when it's not directly together with it,
which is the way רש"י Rashi reads it. Anyways, דברי רבי שמעון,
divrei Rabbi Shimon, that's what Rabbi Shimon says. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yosi, בכולן אני רואה להחמיר. bechulan ani ro'eh lehachmir. All of
these things you said are not a problem, I say it is
a problem. Full weight of קדושה kedusha with וכולן אני רואה להחמיר.
v'khulam ani ro'eh l'hachmir. במה דברים אמורים, Bamah devarim amurim, now when
is all this said? That there is, it's not as weighty קדושה,
kedusha at least according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, בקדשי מזבח, bekadshei
mizbe'ach, sacrifices. אבל בקדשי בדק הבית, Aval bekadshei bedek habayit,
things that are sanctified to the Temple treasury, מועלין בהן כדין מעילה.
mo'alin bahen kedin me'ilah. Okay, so here you have a debate where
everybody agrees that with things sanctified to Temple treasury, it has full
קדושה. kedusha, Within קדשי מזבח kadshei mizbe'ach sacrifices, you basically have that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's a weaker קדושה, kedusha. you bring
it but there's a lot of implications are not there, and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says it's full קדושה. kedusha, Now, at least though
according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he said explicitly that there's no
תמורה. So that's one of the effects of it being a weaker
קדושה. kedusha. So that answers our question. Now, of course, it answers
our question in a somewhat uninteresting way from the perspective of our
question. 'Cause our question was, is it linked to sin or is
it linked to, you know, the metaphysical? And here we say he
can't do it, but not because of the sin issue. He can't
do it because of the קדושה kedusha, issue, right? So it doesn't
help me have to do it, it answers the technical question, but
we still don't know the issue about its relationship to the idea
of sin. All we're saying is he can't do it because the
קדושה kedusha, is different. So let's see at least how the גמרא
Gemara, responds to this. So the גמרא says, קתני מיהא אינו עושה
תמורה, Katani miha eino oseh tmura, it says you don't make תמורה.
So the גמרא, ורמי בר חמא, v'Rami bar Chama, so what's, so
how, so obviously there's your answer. So it says no, ורמי בר
חמא בהקדיש עובד כוכבים להתכפר עובד כוכבים לא קמיבעיא ליה. v'Rami bar
Chama behikdish oved kochavim l'hitkaper oved kochavim lo kamibaya leh. He would
tell you, look, if a non-Jew sanctified an animal that it should
be his קרבן, I'm admitting that that is not my question. There
the קדושה kedusha. level is lower and does not allow for תמורה.
כי קמיבעיא ליה, Ki kamibaya leh, what's my question? בהקדיש עובד כוכבים
ומתכפר בישראל. Behikdish oved kochavim umitkaper b'Yisrael. You can actually sanctify an
animal to be somebody else's sacrifice. James needs to bring an עולה,
olah, I sanctify my cow to be James's עולה. olah. That works.
I'm the מקדיש, makdish, he's the מתכפר, mitkaper, he's the one being
atoned. So if a non-Jew sanctified an animal for a ישראל, Yisrael,
then we imagine, now this is interesting,
because when we said a non-Jew's sacrifice is lower קדושה, you imagine
it means 'cause the non-Jew was the one who did the sanctifying
of it. But here we're actually suggesting no, maybe it's because it
was to be a קרבן for the non-Jew. Fundamentally the בית המקדש,
I mean, ביתי בית תפילה יקרא לכל העמים, beiti beit tefilla yikarei
l'chol ha'amim, but nevertheless the priority, you know, the focus is for
the Jewish people. So a קרבן of a for a non-Jew doesn't
have the same קדושה. But let's say a non-Jew sanctified it for
ישראל. Yisrael. So that would be a scenario where he imagines it
would have the same קדושה, full קדושה. And now we can ask
our question, if it has the full קדושה, can the non-Jew now
make a תמורה? Not if it's based on sin, the answer would
be no. If it's based on קדושה, the answer will be yes.
And we are able to still maintain our question in an interesting
way rather than answering it in a less interesting way about the
level of קדושה. So we will return tomorrow to see what the
answer to this question is.